howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show today's guest is John Rob
thinker and writer about global level
systems and conflicts his main platform
is global guerrillas you can google it
hi Jim thanks for having me on John has
a most interesting background he was a
graduate of the US Air Force Academy he
then served something like seven years
in the Air Force before resigning to
return to the private sector for getting
a master's from Yale he went to work for
Forrester Research back in the 90s it
was the leading big picture and
strategic technology research house fact
I knew George colony there reasonably
well very interesting guy in fact that
Forster John's the guy who initiated a
dedicated service for some newfangled
thing called the Internet and I guess
that kind of worked out huh yeah it did
it did yeah George colony was the editor
on my first report which is kind of cool
very interesting guy fact when I was at
Thompson we thought about buying our way
into that industry you know buying
Forrester and then another smaller one
and I went up met with George chatted
with him about it was clear he was not
interested in selling but he and I hit
it off so well we basically stayed for
quite a while correspondence and friends
and sent each other books and what have
you really enjoyed him he was a good guy
after being at Forster hey like I could
do this shit these other clowns are
starting company so we went out and
became a tech entrepreneur co-founded a
company called Gomez a performance
measurement company which was acquired
in 2009 by Compuware he was also
president of user land a company that's
not that well remembered today but was
extraordinarily influential in its day
it's fair to say that no company has
that was more influential in developing
what came to be known as blogging well
they didn't quite invent it they were as
far as I recall the first real
popularizer of the RSS format for
distributing and aggregating blogs was
that right John yeah Dave Winer actually
was a co-author of it yeah and and we
did our assess and then we combined it
with blogging and the output became a
network blogging system
which is exactly what you see with
Facebook and Twitter and the like or
medium yeah sort of a classic network
blogging system in 2004 John started his
blog global guerrillas where he's posted
a long series of deep and thoughtful
analysis of current events the world
situation tactics and strategy and
perspectives about the future will work
their way up to deep things but let's
start with your take on the recent
attack on the Saudi Arabian fuel
processing center what do we know what's
going on well um we were completely
surprised
across the board we didn't have any
human or SIGINT indication that the
attack was coming so is a failure of
intelligence and then there was a
failure of battlefield intelligence
battlefield awareness we weren't able to
detect the attack until it was actually
commencing and in process it went by the
aegis destroyers in the Gulf you know
with their air defense systems
state-of-the-art I don't you know flat
pancake flat terrain which is like in a
perfect environment to detect missiles
and drones and then you know all the
Patriot missile batteries I think the
Saudis had 88 this attack blew right
past them - they didn't detect it at all
essentially no I know the only thing
that actually triggered was the the guns
attached to the point defense system set
up at the at the processing facility so
essentially what we had is a you know
completely surprising attack and
probably the most well defended most
important oil or energy hub in the world
it's a you know for years I mean for
decades everyone's been speculating in
at you know how this facility would be
attacked it's you know AB cake is
attached to guar and guar is the the
massive oil field that's produced I
think a succeed is 70% of all of Saudi
Arabia's oil produces 5 million barrels
a day little over and it's been doing
that
for 250 years and abdicate processes it
takes out the sulfur it does it's a you
know a monstrous facility has you know
very expensive equipment yet you know
it's obviously very vulnerable to this
new type of attack drones relatively
slowly being able to maneuver to come in
from directions that aren't anticipated
flying very low using relatively
inexpensive equipment to do it you can
do it with GPS you can do it with you
know staggering the launch so the the
drones come in you know every minute or
simultaneously from different directions
so that's what we know you have the
classic asymmetric warfare as I
understood it these drones were maybe 10
or 20 thousand dollars each something
like that and whether they shoot bring
in 28 of them something like that so
you're talking you know less than a
million dollars and you know if they've
followed it up with a couple of more
they could have completely disrupted the
oil economy right oh yeah exactly uh you
know the oil the oil market obviously is
is it very inelastic market and you know
market and elasticity means that you
know once you get into a little bit of
shortage the prices can go way up
because people continue to buy they
don't have the ability to switch it out
and we've been in a surplus for quite a
while and to have this kind of taking
off you know five and a half million
barrels a day of production taken off
the table instantaneously put us right
into that you know edge of shortage
condition so any more loss would have
shot the price up well over a hundred
bucks and the last time that happened
you know we had the global recession
that kicked off the financial collapse
yeah and if remember the other thing
about the commodities explosion in 2007
it led to revolutions all across the
Middle East right right yeah oh yeah all
kinds of second-order effects so what
was the failure mode I mean not only did
it were there us assets in the area but
the Saudis spend vastly more than let's
say the Iranians do on defense how could
this happen well I mean they don't have
any drone defense but it's you know it's
the asymmetry you know you you can have
drones coming in from Iraq and from
Yemen and from opponents that you don't
anticipate having to fight or at least
at that distance I mean we had some
warning I mean Yemenis had attacked
other facilities they attacked the
east-west pipeline just a couple months
prior you know a pumping facility
successfully using drones so there was a
warning that this was occur but
you know this is classic systems
disruption is it's hitting critical
nodes in these big networks that we
depend on and causing all sorts of
cascades of failure and there's really
not a easy way to fix that in fact I
don't think there's a a good way to fix
it at all you just have to reduce your
dependency on those networks many other
thing of course a truism in military
history is militaries tend to fight the
last war right so they have the aegis
ships out there and the Gulf looking to
shoot down f-14s or something but
instead come tiny little drones flying
low and slow oops
our you know billion-dollar Aegis ships
can't even deal with those right that's
great the other hand if someone had
actually been forwardly thinking and
said well wait a minute let's wargame
this out asymmetric drone warfare is
gonna be an obvious thing you know we
could have spent vastly smaller sums and
built counter drone systems you know
more point defense because fortunately
drones are slow and they're not stealthy
at least the ones that were used here so
if you rang the facility with point
defence weapons with high granular radar
practically shot them all down for not a
whole lot of money well it actually may
end up being more expensive to do that
all the you know the point defense
effort because you have to defend a lot
of different points and there's a you
can't get the economies of scale you get
on these systems with you know hundreds
of miles of range yeah that's true that
on the other hand for a small number of
very vulnerable and ultra high-value
ones like the oil facility it makes a
lot of sense right probably not going to
defend every government office building
interesting where do you think the
attack came from did it come from Yemen
did it come from
Orion or do we know yet um combination I
think of an attack from Yemen and from
Iraq from Iraq yeah there's the Iranians
staged an attack from Iraq ah okay okay
so yeah there wasn't any real easy way
to detect it unless you were looking in
those directions of course they should
have been but they were Pearl Harbor all
over again all right should have but
they didn't for the Saudis that
definitely was Pearl Harbor I mean a
really the big impact on them is that it
really screwed with their IPO yeah
they're taking a ramp go public and you
know edit
two trillion-dollar offering in this
easily slammed half a trillion off of
that or more because now the system is
actually shown to be vulnerable and that
they're incapable of defending it and
yeah and from bigger perspective it
ought to substantially undercut you know
their the whole position of the Saudi
regime you know the world's last
absolute monarchy right right in feudal
empire right get rid of them sons of
bitches right but and this you know
shows the world that they can be taken
down easily right so probably the
Iranians and other folks have said all
right when the day comes and we decide
we really want to take the Saudis out
we'll just knock all their oil off leave
it out for a year or two just constant
marine of these damn things right and
nothing to do about it
you know that's gonna as you say gonna
very much reduce the interest of other
people and investing large sums of money
into that area at least along as the
Saudi regime remains in power yeah but
also kind of exposed that the fact that
the u.s. really isn't as interested in
the Middle East as they used to be
because we produce so much oil
absolutely and has changed our
perspective I mean we made the strategic
error a grand strategic error of
focusing on the Middle East as a primary
hot spot as something that we should and
needed to actively engage with back in
at the end of the Cold War you know
largely based on projections that we
weren't going to be able to produce oil
and that the oil market would continue
to contract due to Chinese demand
ramping up and that the US production
was over and that was completely
reversed about halfway through the Iraq
war proven to be false and that you know
initial strategic decision has been
yielding nothing but damage to the US
since then they are the forever wars
right what a stupid ideas wrecked though
one question about that why is there
been no response to the Iranian attack
you know Trump was all huffing and
puffing then didn't do anything um I
think Trump is he's very big on rhetoric
is particularly when it comes to
international engagements but he's very
negative on getting engaged in a foreign
conflict
he just shied away from it but I also
think that the Saudis that didn't want
to increase attentions they didn't want
to engage in a full-scale war with Iran
while fighting in in Yemen while trying
to you know refinance basically the
Kingdom by going you know going to the
public markets they would have totally
tanked that for as long as he as long as
we could project so you know the Saudis
saying no and then and then Trump's
natural inclination he's he's placed
trade strategy ahead of national
security strategy used to trade used to
be just a you know slave to the national
security you know whatever was best in
terms of you know the security of the
global system we we let the the trade
strategy accommodate that and he's
reversed that relationship national
security is now and enthralled to the
the trade strategy whatever improves our
trade status yeah like a current example
I if it's true I think it probably is is
that Trump gave assurances to the
Chinese that we would not meddle in Hong
Kong if they would provide some
concessions on trade correct and that
was all leaked out I mean all that
recent China stuff was all leaked from
China to the US papers they basically
did the did exactly the same thing that
you know Russia has been doing you know
interfere in our national politics but
no one really paid attention to that
because it's anti-trump yeah well the
only thing is it and this is the thing
that's a little bit disingenuous about
this rush of stuff every country has
been messin in every other country's
elections right
people forget Obama men meddled in both
the brexit vote and the previous Israeli
elections right he came out and said who
he wanted I mean that definitely
meddling people don't mention that so
and the always eyes if the u.s. hasn't
meddled in elections all over the world
all the time I am a little surprised by
the disingenuous nests of the focus on
though these bad Russians yes that we
should be making sure we harden
ourselves against those things but the
thing that they're the first people to
ever do this is very silly
let's change directions here a little
bit move up the stack in terms of
conceptual stuff you've popularized the
terms the resistance and the insurgent
see often compare and contrast the two
and compare the two is kind of
interacting systems could you briefly
describe them and tell us how those
movements are impacting our political
situation today okay well the concept is
is that the American political scene is
now the battleground between two social
networks in a weaponized social networks
that have taken over the political
process started with the insurgency
which is the rejection of the
establishment that bolted and put Trump
into office the insurgency is a maneuver
based insurgency it disrupts systems it
causes chaos and because of that chaos
it disrupts the decision-making process
of of the opposition the established
opposition as well as any Network
opposition and it's been fairly
effective I mean they put Trump in
office it's maintaining his popularity
Trump is a natural in terms of that kind
of maneuver based disruptive strategies
he has a lots of what got what's called
a fast transiency moves from one topic
to the next one disruption to the next
there's never really any time for the
the opposition to get build a momentum
in terms of opposition on any specific
point the resistance is the network
that's been most effective at combating
the insurgency and it found it
it's purchased in in the identity side
very values focused its puritanical in
many respects doesn't put up with
violations of values and it's in the
process of taking over the Democratic
Party and you know we're seeing the kind
of compromised mainstream candidates
being a you know throw it to the side
like Biden and anyone who is like who
would try to straddle the middle ground
AOC for instance is you know the perfect
example of of the resistance fighter the
resistance participant and both of these
networks are open source meaning there's
not any one specific person that that's
leader those those people that you see
at the front tend to be more like
a weaponized version of the network
there's lots of you know conflicting
ideas within these open-source networks
but there are you know all agreed on a
single you know animating purpose so
that you know that's just there's the
core of the idea yeah let's talk a
little bit about these networks right we
can over and on Facebook we have a group
called rally point alpha I think you
remember that aren't you John mm-hmm I'm
a manager of it I guess ah okay
the that's right that's a group where we
based on an essay by Jordan Hall a group
of us have gotten together and talked
about how collective intelligence
networks decentralized networks have
really completely changed the game or at
least they've changed it yet but they're
in the process of changing the game
right could you talk a little bit about
the nature of these networks and I
started looking at networks as a new
kind of organizational framework after
the Iraq invasion I was seeing results
coming from from that engagement that
weren't fitting you know the the media
narratives or the analytical narratives
coming out of the establishment so um
what I saw was something similar to what
I was seeing on the Internet it was an
open source framework were lots of
disparate groups come together to
operate as a single unit but they're
only tied together through what's called
a plausible promise or the idea of what
one single simple goal that everyone can
agree on often it's like no more
corruption or remove this specific
leader in Iraq there were you know 70
different groups lots of very very small
groups through you know lots of
different flavors of jihadi lots of
different types of nationalists and
Baathists with or without Saddam and
criminal groups and these groups all
seem to be able to work together
effectively by focusing on rejecting the
United States as the you know single
goal that United him if left alone in
the room they would kill each other
immediately but they were able to put
that to the side one one thing we saw
with open source networks like this is
that they're extremely innovative
at least in the in the Iraq war they did
more in six months and the Irish
Republican Army did in 20 years in terms
of innovation it was very very quick we
had a three billion dollar program for
counter a IEDs
whenever we put out a counter they
countered our counter within two weeks
and our release schedule was every three
months to six months so they were
beating us very quickly and they shared
those innovations there wasn't really
any you know lockdown I'm gonna keep
this for my my own group they shared it
freely among each other each group was
able to copy what the other group did
and apply it very quickly and there was
a also sharing through the through the
media kind of what I called stigma G
it's a this idea that it comes from
insects you know when an ant you know
finds a little food what they do is they
leave a chemical trail you know as they
carry the food back that chemical trail
acts as a signal for other ants to
follow and find the food and each ant
that does that adds more chemicals to
that trail until the food is exhausted
and in the case of an open-source
insurgency you know every group that
made a successful attack either by
innovating on the target selection or
innovating on that on the method of
attack had it covered in the press and
had it covered you know through online
coverage you know self posting often
through their own videos and that served
as kind of a chemical trail that this
target was now available for attack this
method works and then everyone else can
copy it and they copied it until it
didn't work and they moved on to the
next innovation so there's some of the
attributes of open-source groups and how
they innovate and how they organized its
if you can get your head around that
kind of core structure it makes
understanding what the resistance in the
and the you know present-day insurgency
looks like and how they operate how did
you could you couldn't take that model
on that now remap it to say the
emergence of the insurgency in the u.s.
in 2016 yeah so uh you know what we saw
in kind of the Trump insurgency was that
you know Trump was put up forward as a
weapon he was really good at you know
disrupting things but there were
hundreds of different subgroups
supporting that campaign and you're
constantly innovating I mean you had
like even though that reddit group that
that pro-trump reddit group and they had
300,000 members I was interviewed on
that just a week after Trump was it's
kind of interesting all of these groups
were all coming up with different types
of memes different types of angles of
attack on different aspects of the
Democratic strategy constantly coming up
with you know ways of countering what
was going on at the on the Democratic
side and the Democrats were the classic
bureaucracy they you know they were
spending gobs of money on media and in a
professional help people consultants
said you know new elections better than
anyone else they had a you know big
ground game lots of people on the ground
they had huge databases but they were
all tightly bound up and centrally
controlled and even with all the media
on their on their side you know
supporting their messaging the
insurgency was still able to route
around it that's why I mean is it's the
reason why that the the Russian effort
as ham-handed as it was and and kind of
diffuses it was was you know able to
slot right in you know it was just one
member out of the hundreds that were
participating in in the insurgency and
that if something was successful if
something had some legs in terms of a
new idea a new angle of attack a new
disruption Trump was really good at
taking it out and then elevating it and
using it in his tweet stream then I
would echo back to these things and be
upregulated the group you were talking
about on read it's called the Donald I
believe right yeah the Donald yeah I
built the system a couple years back
that parsed the Donald in real-time and
ran it through a bunch of analytical
software and sorted memes and showed
trend lines and all that because I had
determined that the Donald was the
convergence point for the what you would
call the insurgency network yet
relatively few memes were actually
invented on the Donald but it's where
they were propagated
and where they got validity so things
would be cooked up in 4chan or ei-chan
or in wackier places than that people
would post them to the donald and if
they got uploaded there then they might
get picked up by Infowars or Breitbart
or even and then from there they go to
Fox News then try to pick them up and
then he broadcasts them and then up
regulates that whole message and then
there's themes and variations on every
new invention so it's very much an
evolutionary fast-tracking kind of
system as you were describing exactly
exactly you know you throw it against
the wall and see what sticks but but
there is a but there is a network
structure it's not just completely
chaotic you know there are convergent
zones there are amplifiers
there's the maximum amplifier which was
Trump's tweet stream and it somehow you
know came together and worked good
enough is the insurgency still existing
that is it still improving or is it kind
of done its thing and in a senile State
these days well I mean a disruptive
insurgency typically has to have an
enemy to focus on all right and you know
what we saw in at least in regular
warfare we also saw it in the big you
know open source protests that you know
swept the Islamic world we saw just
recently with the in Puerto Rico and
other open source protests that was
successful is that it has to have an
opposition a single point of opposition
to focus all their efforts on um so it's
been in largely dormant you know since
the election and I start ramping up
again when when the election starts
regardless I'd still been successful
enough to allow Trump to still have a
forty four percent approval rating yeah
now the resistance
yeah the resistance is different it you
know if fights in the moral realm you
know whereas the maneuver is is all
about disrupting your ability to think
rationally and cogently the moral realm
of you know is about attacking your your
cohesion and the resistances was formed
largely online just to you know fight
the unstoppable you know Trump
insurgency you know where the
traditional democratic party has been
largely ineffective where the you know
all the you know established players
have been you know ineffective the media
has been extraordinarily ineffective it
that's stopping Trump you know here
comes the resistance and the resistance
is now feeding you know moral arguments
and and trying to shape the media shape
the Democratic Party shape all of the
institutions even corporate space and
and try to force it into a mode that
will allow it to confront Trump
I mean think of all the more arguments
being put on the big tech companies to
start to censor Trump to Center the
insurgency to knock media player media
personalities off of YouTube to delete
Trump's Twitter account to put in place
you know
automated versions of censorship that
would allow this to never occur again
these are you know moral warfare is very
similar to what we're also seeing in
China and and it's social credit system
and it's a you know war on anyone who
you know says anything negative about
China more warfare is is a very
effective but has the potential of
becoming you know very puritanical and
very restrictive and very in a cost
stagnation because it doesn't allow any
deviants will go to China later I got a
couple of detailed questions about China
but back to the resistance sure the
structure of the resistance because it
isn't directly coupled with mainstream
media there has to be some human energy
that keeps it going or the Donald had
six hundred thousand people or whatever
it is
where's where are the bodies and is
there any convergent zones in the
resistance where ideas come together and
get up regulated it says oh yeah now the
network to apology what's it look like
it's twitter twitter is the the focal
point for the resistance and its
millions of people and those that
Twitter conversation is constantly when
they find you know at the personal level
when they find you know violations of
what they consider in their value system
their moral code though they'll point
that out and it goes on to Twitter first
and everyone responds to that expresses
their outrage and that's where they
reach in also to
different organizations if they find a
bureaucrat that's not doing you know
following what they consider the correct
behavior they'll reach in and touch that
person directly call them out
yeah Twitter is the main vehicle before
the resistance okay that seems to make
sense be interesting to see how these
networks morph as we go into 2020 and
the stakes move up right will the
insurgency invade hooah determine
whether funding of insurgency people on
Twitter I see both sides all the time on
Twitter it doesn't work as well yeah
they'd searches who doesn't work as well
on Twitter as the resistance it's more
of a broadcast medium so that you know
they're they're moving what they do is
you know through their conversation is
they move towards a consensus on a
specific topic or specific you know
value and when they reach that consensus
then they enforce it
it's consensus seeking which is
different from the insurgency I mean
that if you had the I just was in the
process of writing this this month's
report is about that or one of the
reports I'm writing this month it's it's
this new political spectrum is that you
have on the one side this consensus
seeking consensus driven value system
which is the resistance and then on the
other side you have this disruptive
capability and they're in tension and
you know the network that's driving the
this this new value system has the
ability to reach into all the old
bureaucracies and and down to the
individual level and and set them in a
you know in a very specific direction
and the disruptive capability comes in
and if those if that value system is too
restrictive or pointing in the wrong
direction the the insurgency would
disrupt it and cause it to reset itself
or go back to a an earlier stage you
follow me on that absolutely in fact
it's a perfect transition to my next
point you've written quite a bit about
coherence right and especially about the
ever-growing decoherence in the West you
know frankly I'm coming more and more to
believe that an unconscious libido for
social coherence is the invisible force
field that's driving a lot of our social
turmoil and you know what you just said
resonates with that a lot right the
resistance
is people who unconsciously are starved
for coherence you know the market has
replaced the community the government
has replaced the family we live in flat
land where no one really needs to have
any adherence to anything to live in
modern Democratic liberalism groups like
the resistance offer a coherence right
right it's a new brand of coherence and
a coherence is very powerful if we look
at you know work from people like Peter
terchen who has studied the rise and
fall of Empires and the emergence of
small Borderlands groups that bring down
empires etc he always points to a word
he uses a Subbiah of a very similar to
coherence that would seem to indicate
that in a fight resistance might have an
advantage over insurgency if resistance
is based on coherence and insurgency
isn't unless you have coherence among
the around the wrong idea Ori that you
value stability over everything else so
if you had to draw the political
spectrum at a global scale you would
have China on one side and Russia on the
other China is obviously you know more
successful but it's just started to lock
down process and if they achieve total
coherence and totally enforced by their
social credit system and and and the
like you can see the stagnation threat
there where no new ideas are allowed
because they can violate or disrupt the
status on the other hand do you know too
much disruption you end up you know
corrupt like Russia org Trump yeah you
see exactly the same battle here in the
US you have the kind of this Chinese
value lock down on the one side and then
you see this kind of corrupt disruption
on the other side I think that's
actually a benefit I think that's
actually the best place to be is at that
edge that dynamic edge between the two
and that will allow us to maintain them
the maximum creativity without falling
completely apart going forward whereas
the other sides are you know they're
gonna they're screwed yeah the Russians
have lost all our innovative capacity
through pure
option right there's right no way for
anyone to create anything without having
it stolen essentially and as you point
out we'll go on to the Chinese here next
but the other Chinese face the potential
risk of becoming stultifyingly coherent
right and right in fact I have a term I
like to use maybe this is similar to
your edge between the two I call it
coherent pluralism there seems to be
took my mind to error points one is too
much coherence think of the Middle Ages
right at some level or fascism or
Marxist Leninist and then the other
extreme is no coherence you know
essentially chaotic space Somalia and
it's in its worst days etc and Trump
seems to be a pretty incoherent
character in his own right and maybe the
right place is to right-size the
coherent kernel and but then make it a
clear part of our called the
Jeffersonian Madisonian operating system
as they did with religion that we have
pluralism outside the core and yet that
seems to be something that humans have a
hard time doing they want to totalize
one way or the other they want it to be
you know radical libertarians or you
know high-end the utopians and trying to
find that balance of the right amount of
coherence to make a society feel good
for people I mean I would argue our
current Western society has two little
coherence we don't have enough duty to
our society and you know there's no real
sense of belonging to a society it's all
transactional and commercial but on the
other hand stultifying Chinese
neo-fascism isn't the answer either so
maybe something in between is a way to
think about it coherence but bound it
yeah I mean the grand historical
narrative behind this at least from my
perspective is that the Internet is the
equivalent of the printing press in
terms of his effect on society and I
look at it through the kind of McLuhan
Marshall McLuhan lens it's a that this
technology is rewiring us it's changing
the way we think at a very root level
and that it's that change is going to
change the way we organize their society
and I mean with the printing press you
saw
the emergence of bureaucracies as a
replacement to kind of the feudal noble
system you saw the shattering of the
universal church religion has been in a
downward slope since then in terms of
its influence you saw the rise of
democracy at least the institutionalized
democracy you know and you saw the rise
of science made possible by the printing
press it you know they kind of these
bureaucracies have changed everything
and they wouldn't have been possible
without that without that kind of
technological change so we have the you
know the internet hitting us and social
networking really has been the the big
mover within that and that you know but
we're being rewired the old bureaucratic
system is becoming less effective and
the the old kind of tribal element
nationalism has become less effective in
terms of keeping us connected no there's
three different decision-making systems
that we've kind of cobbled together to
kind of produce the system we live in
now as I got this David Rowan felts you
know Tim and framework it's a tribe's
institutions markets and networks and
institutions beating the bureaucracies
and the bureaucratic kind of
organizational cockroach that that
transformed us from the ancient world
into the modern world and tribes which
provided us kind of a connection it
allowed us to trust each other enough
that we could make decisions as a group
you know if you're a part of the same
tribe you ascribe to the same narrative
tribal narrative you know why you are
special and why you should remain
together you can trust the information
that comes from with that person when
you shatter a tribe like we're seeing
now you can't trust the information
that's provided by the people who aren't
in your drive when you fundamentally
distrust it so when people look at
what's coming out of the media or out of
you know anyone on Trump side I mean
it's fundamentally distrusted regardless
of whether it's correct or not so those
you know
tribal tribal system and the bureaucracy
is fading the institutional part is
fading markets are being you know
relatively easy to corrupt and
concentrate they become over
concentrated and you know replicated
many of the bad features of central
planning and so here comes networking
and this kind of you know broad this new
kind of decision-making system and how
does that work you know and we're just
finding out that it has two functions
that can be a disruptive function throw
things into chaos and and that it could
also can set consensus or come to
consensus on values on new sets of
values values at work and that they can
reach down into organizations into
bureaucracies and the big battle being
in the future they'll be able to reach
down into a corporate land and force
corporate compliance these value systems
and presumably they'll be competing ones
and maybe you know we have now the
resistance is taking that form but it
would seem natural that there will have
to be a other side to that so there'll
be at least two and probably more than
that
competing coherent quasi tribal systems
so far there it only looks like they're
gonna be to China and the rest of the
world well I was thinking even within
our society right oh no I I don't think
they can last I mean the these networks
tend to be they tend to expand and crush
any opposition within their space it's
it's a I don't I don't I don't see it I
think I think the the overall direction
and this is like another McLuhan thing
is that we're headed towards this you
know grand consolidation at a at a you
know at a network a global network level
and that you know all of this fighting
that we're going through and and in this
struggle that we're seeing over the long
over the next couple decades will be
about which system ends up becoming the
dominant one I wonder if that's really
true let me if we take a look at recent
history if we look at the nation-states
they've been breaking down into smaller
and smaller units right because of
bureaucracies less effective in a
complex environment yeah and also I
think people are looking for coherence
also because my other argument why do
the Scots want to get away from
the UK why do you know why is the
Catalonians so insistent on breaking
away from the Spanish which they've been
you know married to for five hundred
years but that's a lot that's doable
because there is now a network component
that can allow them to interact them and
there's a EU granted there's a
intermediary step there but it being
part of the same network allows you to
fragment at the nation-state level they
don't have to be as big yeah you can
still be coherent still be able to talk
to each other as as friends as part of
the same unit yeah you have to have like
a minimum standards of interconnect
think of it as the you know the internet
it's like these minimum standards
allowed the whole network to assemble
you have to have the same value system
as a minimum standard in order to to
work together and you can fragment the
nation-states down to nothing done to
micro levels and if you have that same
value set it allows that to happen
coherently and actually if maybe even
economically efficiently because the
networks can correct replace many of the
things the nation-state was doing
economically not everything but many of
the things so a nation-state of five
million people is now quite feasible
right yeah and also that the network
allows you to love these small states to
avoid becoming you know prey to large
multinational corporations to I mean
it's you know these networks have the
ability to change the policy or change
the alignment of large multinationals so
if you were running the extinction
rebellion you wouldn't be protesting
government you'd be picking out a
company as a victim and forcing them
into alignment and one month after a
month you know again and again and again
until they until you have sufficient
number of companies aligned with you
there's another good example of an
emergent coherent group from the Nets is
the extinction rebellion I've been
saying for some time that one could go a
long long long way I could be the you
know the the unexpected invention of
Christianity equivalent right that
twelve random dudes and Galilee changed
the world in this case it could be
whoever started the extinction rebellion
could end up changing the world yeah
they'd probably end up folding into the
larger you know resistance Network
whatever that you can call it what
at that point because it's not really
resistance so much as it is a kind of a
value consensus is that you know the
other thing that this that everyone's
battling over is this idea of being able
to set the conditions of the AI so
socially eyes that are being developed
and I mean the winner sets those
conditions and what I mean by that is a
is that what we're finding with AI at
least from my perspective is that it
really isn't really great at producing a
human equivalent intelligence I mean we
don't even properly utilize the you know
seven billion people we have right now
with the human level intelligence
creating more of that is just kind of a
useless activity where it really seems
to be shining and based on the amount of
data that's available and the data is
highly correlated with the quality of
the the AI is a more is better is that
in this social space it's great at
managing it learns a lot about managing
the connections between us and was we
know in complex systems the connections
matter more than the individual units so
managing that that connection space is
what AI is really going to shine at
doing and we have the potential then to
create social systems that are
technological artifacts and that we'll
have one from China and we'll have them
from the rest of the world and setting
those the goals that this AI is going to
try to accomplish or try to you know
instantiate in this society is going to
be the biggest fight ever I mean you
know who's gonna actually control it I
mean it's an incredible power if you get
it wrong you wither as a society you
destroy whatever you built and of course
it's quite a growing suspicion from both
team red and team blue about the
unprecedented power that Google and
Facebook in particular have to
manipulate the lens with which we see
the world it's a very interesting
difficult problem and frankly they may
be good guys but I'm a Madisonian I
don't trust any single source of power
so if I were to suggest you know the
road forward to make sure that we don't
end up with a corrupt set of lenses from
the googles and the Facebook's as we
need competitors and fortunately there
are people working on competitors you
know under cup under overcoming the
network effects of Google and Facebook
is not easy so they won't be general
solutions initially maybe a network for
you know the hundred thousand people who
are most see most clearly let's Sally
say or the million people most
interested in the extinction rebellion
who will set up a powerful and coherent
social network she'll then aggregate
people over time and in that way we can
it's probably the safest way to hedge
the bet from the Facebook's and Google's
implementing a set of filters and AIS
that implement their vision of the good
and the true oh yeah there's the
bottom-up top-down you know conflict you
know the insurgency tends to focus on
trying to prevent these systems from
having any influence they don't want any
controls they don't want any any
influence undue influence coming from
the big social ai's
I mean those are the biggest a eyes we
interact with a long shot I mean two and
a half billion people on Facebook
interact with a you know social AI right
now every day and I need you know
there's all this pressure right now I
obviously from the resistance to kind of
come up with the consensus values that
are written into this AI know there's
lots of lots of conflict points I the
only the only thing that would be
tough for a bottoms-up version of this
is the data the way these systems learn
is that they require tons of data they
don't work off of you know the kind of
first principles that we've derived over
time through science and you know if you
can't get that data you can't get good
so it's got to be a whoever whoever
comes up with something new has to find
a way to get more data well at least
have to have enough data the question is
what is sufficient for the task and you
don't throw out a hypothesis maybe you
know an intense coherence is enough to
get a founder community that's big
enough which might be a hundred thousand
to a million that the network can start
to tune itself from so you use coherence
to jumpstart and build an environment
that's perceived to be of higher quality
than the kind of flatland of Facebook
and then once you have a critical mass
built on coherence then you have the
numbers to you know start to use the
technology to you know and if your ideas
are good enough and your coherence is
pleasing enough to people you will find
you will get defectors I mean this is
you know you I think you followed this
discussion called game a and game B yep
then and essentially that's the argument
from the game beers that you don't need
300 million people in the United States
to be game B on day one you need some
critical mass much much much smaller and
you make it highly coherent and highly
pleasing to be part of and have good
tools and gradually you get defectors
from gaming game B gets stronger and
stronger and it's less dependent on the
quality of the AI is in the short term
because it has something else coherence
and a plan and good quality of life so I
think there are you know you don't have
to attack strength to strength as we
know in asymmetric warfare you don't
attack strength the strength you attack
somewhere else you know game B will
attack through coherence and quality of
existence rather than by brute numbers
and kind of brute force AI that's the
game B hypothesis yeah I would look in
terms of evaluating those those
alternatives I would focus on the call
of the interactions if that system if
that game be system is providing higher
quality interactions than the
alternative more so than the at the end
states for the individual participants
if that you know it's like for instance
um did you ever read a medic in echo
from Bruce Sterling no okay great short
science fiction story Bruce is probably
one of the best science fiction writers
I've ever come across
you know his matrix is amazing and
maneki-neko is a great it's online you
could probably find it for free and it
has a system that is a gifting system
that kind of takes off in this direction
it comes out of nowhere
you know like early tribal systems were
always you know gifting and that barter
was only where you cleared the
transaction at the end of the you know
end of the engagement was only done
between enemies right and that we scaled
the enemy component all the way up to a
to a global system because it we
couldn't maintain the trust necessary on
the tribal side to and find a way to
scale it is that in that in the
manekineko
universe it they had a system that kept
track of basically your karma and kept
tracked over the needs and wants the
immediate needs and wants as well as the
long-term needs and once of the
individuals that are part of the network
and that they were constantly gifting
you know connecting people and saying if
you gift this to this person right now
you will gain you know access to more
gifts future in the future and your
prioritization will go up so if somebody
just lost a job or had a bad day and
they in the system knew that they'll
have coffee and they're sitting at a
park bench and kind of thinking oh my
god the world is terrible they would
interact with somebody in the network
and say bring a coffee to this person
this is the type of coffee that they
like and you do it and they go wow
that's awesome or if they needed a job
of a specific type or an engagement or
or a specific item that's preventing
them from doing or achieving some goal
that the system would interconnect and
allow that interconnection to to
accelerate their their path forward
eventually you know if this system gets
good enough at least in this short story
that it would replace standard economic
engagement because you've got everything
you really true
needed through the gifting process and
that's not far from you know the
thinking of people like Daniel SH mocked
and burger from the game B space right
who was looking for a alternative non
rival risk form of organization for the
means of life that aren't all you know
brutal market-driven and I don't think
we yet know what that looks like but
those are the kind of places that people
are probing on and you know again when
they come they'll come from nowhere
they'll come from a small group of
people who've cooked up a new social
operating system that actually
outcompetes the existing one in terms of
qualitative experience but like you're
absolutely right that the it's like the
hippies right it was fun to be a hippie
it's much more fun to be a hippie than a
straight in 1967 right I was a junior
high school kid so I didn't get to play
that game but you saw it right and so if
game B or some other new startup social
operating system has a better form of
existence for people you can say Mike
Christianity did I mean it was not as
brutal and harsh as Roman life was right
it was much more coherence and taking
care of each other it could you know
gain momentum and go all the way and it
would seem that at this moment our
systems are old and tired and fragile
the life that they're providing for
people while materially better than it's
ever been by a whole lot from the
perspective of meeting our real human
needs I would say not so good right look
at the you know the rates of deaths of
despair amongst middle-aged working
people you know our system is not
working for most people and there's room
for an upstart to come and take it over
right yeah I mean you know when the
printing press it wasn't really quite we
weren't quite sure what would come out
of that in terms of you know new
organizational types new decision-making
systems and I mean who could have
envisioned the the rise of bureaucracy
you know the modern form of bureaucracy
with all the bells and whistles that we
see with you know individuals who are
civil servants who have a certain
ethical code or better content you know
to do their job without you know
immediate recompense all of that would
have come out of that technological
change and how it would transform
governance and transform our lives and
so we're at the same place with networks
you know you know how does that going to
be used to you know transform our life
and then right now we're seeing it on
the you know the open source side and we
see two functions but they're plenty
more out there we just have to discover
them and there's like we can rethink our
democracy for instance ideas like liquid
democracy really could not be done until
you had computer networks and that may
be a better way to govern ourselves not
sure some interesting aspects of it but
it hasn't been tried at scale so but if
it if it turns out to be better
societies that adopt it will out-compete
those that don't well if the way the
networks are operating right now and you
look at you know they've taken over the
political spectrum the new left is not
going to you know follow the pattern of
the old left where it's you know looking
at you know raising taxes are raising
money that's that path is blocked trying
to raise money from you know globalized
wealth is very very tough the regulation
is tough too because the companies in
the and the wealth would you know skip
away so you know the kind of Warren
approach becomes difficult to implement
because there's so many workarounds and
so many ways to you know to beat what
she's proposing the thing that it's
tough to beat and I think it possible
for the traditional corporate
bureaucracies and and and organizations
to be is a left that uses kind of the
presidency in its position in Congress
as kind of a bully pulpit or to also as
a in a coercive system to force
corporations and and and government
bureaucracies into alignment force a
very specific consensus value system
into into place and forcing companies to
provide service and move in a certain
direction if you price your
pharmacological goods to high you get
crushed and if you try to you know take
advantage of a certain market
opportunity at the expense of you know
Americans or then you get crushed
just at the top level at the corporate
level this network can actually reach
deep inside the company and go after
individuals
maybe the redress we've been looking for
right you know the problem since the 70s
has been increasing returns to scale
network businesses have allowed
businesses to get bigger and bigger and
bigger and bigger they've corrupted the
political process and there was no
constraint on them
correct perhaps this form of political
organizing is the redress that that kind
of predatory behavior is calling for
yeah I mean all of our focus right now
is on the disorder the Trump disorder
and and and associated with you plus an
arrow and all those others but the real
danger of the system is too much
governance it's too easy to achieve
you know maximal Hornets you have to
have a little bit of disorder and
disruption order to make sure that it
doesn't up too heavily in that direction
or so you get status and you get you get
repression to get oppression and it's
just built into the system and it can't
get rid of it and your economy suffers
and everything suffers as a result
so in granted you don't want too much
disruption you end up you know this kind
of hyper corruption like you have in
Russia where Putin is like the
wealthiest guy in the world would I you
know I've seen estimates of 200 billion
so it makes him twice as wealthy as
Bezos he uses the network to disrupt
opponents and keep the political process
fluid and it allows him to do basically
anything he wants at the corruption
level in to consolidate power he would
love to be able to do that if he could
get away with it oh yeah if he could but
I mean the thing is I think the tendency
here that the system that's you know
dominant if there was a you know is
towards a hyper coherent system and you
know I don't think we want to go that
direction completely we want to keep it
fluid enough that we can change it and
modify it as it moves forward also we're
in for a world apart but I would say
that you know you draw this picture of a
left coherence doing its thing if we
learned anything from you know our
constitutional history it's always an
arms race there will be a equivalent on
the right very quickly right so there'll
be multiple moralities that are
attempting to subdue
in America and the bureaucracy and
hopefully it'll be more than two and you
know we're locked into two in our
political process by a design flaw in
our institutions which is the
first-past-the-post election method and
our influence networks and you know
let's say moral networks are not
necessarily going to be constrained by
that so instead of two we might have ten
of groups that are attempting to shame
corporations your bureaucracies from
doing bad things and those ten groups
won't agree on what's the good things
and what's the bad thing so that we'll
have a pluralistic way to work that out
I don't see the woke left winning I mean
those people are they just piss off way
too many people and if they ever go too
far they're gonna be in for a big
fucking awakening or Hey yeah well the
right ends up being coming pretty much
just pure disruption or not whoa I don't
see them competing meanings I see this
this natural tension between this like
consensus values versus that you know is
scalable internationally and this
disruptive capability which is basically
saying you know we we wanna many
different viewpoints and we want
different moralities to exist different
you know value systems to exist just
leave us alone of course that may well
be the ethos right if you have a right
and of course that's been at the very
simplistic way that's been the
difference between the left and the
right in politics you know since the
founding they'll leave us alone faction
and we know better than you let us fix
it faction right well that's the that's
the Tom Wolfe quote remember he goes
America is always a danger of fascism
but Europe always becomes fascist is
that the the American right has always
been kind of a leave me alone
the up version and that the European
because of the kind of you know cultural
coherence that they have tends to choose
fascism as arezzo
or as right-wing solution it's not
possible here it's difficult at least
the right you know for instance might
well and it's starting to do fight
against the social platforms trying to
enforce some political orthodoxy on
discourse right right and that would be
a moral argument that in the same way we
always want to independent newspapers
censorship free from content bias right
maybe you have censorship based on
behavior for instance thou shalt not
threaten violence against identifiable
people thou shalt not Doc's etc but
apply those uniformly across the
political spectrum not just to one side
or the other as it seems to be the
tendency these days well that's the job
of the insurgency right is to unearth
those as it involves as it matures is
donor those moral arguments that are
antithetical to the consensus values
that are being put forward and using
those to disrupt those that
consolidation process that's a more you
know beneficial way of looking at it and
that you know if they're those mark
arguments are valid and then they're
gonna be effective in terms of
disrupting that debt consolidation it's
an interesting political time I think
we're in exactly the right place I mean
you know Russia and China are doomed and
then Europe the way they disconnected
themselves from this and trying to hide
a bubble themselves up they are totally
screwed as far as I'm concerned they're
basically saying you know we don't want
industrialization at the beginning of
the Industrial Age de-industrialized
they're becoming fragile they're in
self-imposed fragility they're not
building that the muscle tissue
necessary to operate at this edge and
that you know intellectual muscle or
social muscle tissue they're too worried
about the down side effects and that on
top of that they're not contributing the
data that's going to go into development
of all the AI so that will be
incorporated as services or into the
products that we're going to be buying
in 20 years so I don't know how that's
gonna affect their economy but it can't
be good
it's amazing how how little they've
accomplished in the world in the last 20
or 30 years it's gonna get worse I read
an article I think in the Economist
recently and said that you know 30 years
ago 25% of the 40 largest corporations
on earth were European now it's - and
they're in positions 36 and 38 and what
new thing have they created I can't
think of any what what new has come out
of Europe that had any lasting staying
power over the last 25 or 30 years
nothing right they just have culture
yeah they have culture that they sell
yeah I mean basically they're a tourist
location yep and in fact a science
fiction writer I forget which one had a
near future and essentially he described
Europe as had decided it was going to
become the Museum of Western
civilization and that was all yeah well
let's switch the topic we've hit on two
or three times tangentially I like
really like you to dig it on this guy no
you've thought about this a lot and this
is one or I know I think we have a
certain amount of alignment and that
you've called out the Chinese model as
what it really is which is neo-fascism
right right it's no formal leftism it's
got every aspect of neo-fascism and I've
done the same in a paper I wrote called
in search of the fifth attractor it's
available on medium but where I
described the neo-fascist models exemple
are as China you know data-driven
technologically enabled Social Credit
facial recognition and more tell us
about what you think the Chinese are
trying to do and to what degree do you
think it'll work okay well um you know I
went back to try to get to first
principles I mean water what is the
fascist model at a organizational level
as it you know how does it really work
and you know I went back to the 20th
century and I looked at the three
different models that are merged out of
there that the communist model the
fascist model and the Democratic
capitalism and I really had to do with
how the bureaucracies were organized and
in communism obviously there was one big
bureaucracy it ran everything economy
society etc and that in democratic
capitalism there was a you know
truncated or constrained government
bureaucracy and then there was lots of
corporate bureaucracy so were given free
rein within a you know a large playing
field they stayed relatively loyal
because of the dynamics of the way that
the world worked you know Cold War time
and distance constraints and then you
had fascism which we've pretty much
forgotten we kind of just looked at
jackboots in uniform as signs of fascism
but the organizational the economic
organizational model is pretty
interesting if you really dig into it
you go okay they had a government
bureaucracy and lots of big corporate
bureaucracies that joined with it as a
cohesive whole the government provided a
national goal which aligned all those
big bureaucracies to focus on the
similar goal and they focused less on
competition and more on negotiation then
even if you looked at the unions that
they consolidated all the unions into
big Union and that Union had incredible
pay for all the the members and you know
Industrial Workers even had three cruise
ships that gave out for free for - you
know - all that members I mean it wasn't
just like exploitive it was if you want
all these benefits you have to negotiate
with the big companies in a line on the
same goals now in order to get that
alignment at least at that time the
focus was on you know crude tribalism
and you know the tribal appeals to
identity all the worst kind of stuff
hyper militarism hyper nationalism as a
means of setting those goals for all the
corporate participants and when that was
you know system was crushed
we pretty much forgot about it but now
we have a new system we Democrats in one
beat the communist system in the Cold
War we thought it was going to go
everywhere but what we ended up doing is
globalizing and we allowed the internet
to connect up everyone and there's you
know the system became complex and
divergent and the effectiveness of the
government bureaucracy in in democratic
capitalism became less you carrying less
and less effective less able to raise
money less to be able to control its
borders less able to influence policy
over the long every you know implement a
policy and find it goes wrong within
months and because the system is is
moving too quickly and the corporate
participants you know broke out of their
box and they were able to go
international and they were started to
think international and I think oh we're
not really loyal to the US anymore you
know we're loyal to you know global
audience and we've have different ideals
in different ways of looking at the
world so in response to this chaos what
we're saying is the development of
workarounds and in China was looking at
you know transforming their system they
were you know still relatively
totalitarian and and they opted for a
system that looks very organized and
almost exactly the same way as the
fascist model you can see I work now in
the in the conflict who is Hong Kong is
that they were looking for corporations
to sign on in compliance with you know
enforcing their stance against the
protesters so if they have a protesters
working for them and they recognize that
person as such they are supposed to fire
them
and turn off support for people who
support the protest etc or they're
aligning with their they're aligning
their companies to focus on creating a
social credit network that works in kind
of a Confucian model that is very
patriotic that doesn't allow anyone to
discuss specific topics or criticize the
government
so you know their system is this new
type of fascism so you know you need to
see you can actually see the battle
going you know working on the on the
street level the battle over in a
corporate alignment in Hong Kong is that
you know the government has companies
that they've forced into alignment you
know you're kind of using the fascist
system and the protesters as an
open-source network are trying to punish
those companies so they'll selectively
deface the buildings or the the
storefronts of companies that have opted
to support China so you'll see it just
you know dot dot dot dot dot down the
street as the protest moves forward with
the companies that are fighting them
being punished for that activity so you
know it's it's pretty interesting to see
the the emergence of fascism you can see
the battle in the states is in some ways
very similar to that you know who gets
to control the companies Kenny force
them into alignment to reduce the
instability caused by globalization etc
see that in Russia Russia has already
done it through cross holdings and mafia
style tactics anyway fascism is back
it's probably the true winner of the big
conflict between the three different
systems but it's different and it's not
doesn't look and feel exactly like the
previous version of it history doesn't
repeat but it rhymes right yeah that
would point back to you know those is
again the driver is the libido for
coherence you know the resistance is
trying to produce some coherence at the
intersection of humanity and corporate
America right and again with the danger
of overshooting and become stifling and
just full of you know wrong ideas in
their particular case with some good
some good ideas some bad ideas the
Chinese are also probably at least
partially operating in good faith trying
to produce a better society by
making sure their corporations don't go
hyper capitalist like the West did right
and so again they're attempting to
create more coherence that's minutes I'm
starting to see this as the seer stone
if you start thinking about in terms of
greater versus lesser coherence I think
you start to see what the drivers of all
these various systems are including the
Chinese at least until it enters its
corrupt phase which of course it always
has been more corrupt in the u.s. though
not as corrupt as China could either go
to develop good institutions to
administer sort of a positive fascism or
probably more likely it'll be captured
and become hyper corrupt like Russia I
just become an extraction mechanism for
those who have the levers of power right
yep and coherence is a you know
foundational state you need in order to
make decisions effective decisions so
you know without it nothing is possible
yeah what do you think about the chance
of the Chinese model spreading elsewhere
I mean to degree the Chinese want to do
their thing in China I don't really give
a shit tell you the truth to the degree
they want to put their network model out
into the world and compete the way the
Marxist Leninist is did then that's a
completely different kettle of fish
yeah it's conceptually it works you know
you get the Social Credit system that
works you get their reaction systems
they're putting the we guards through
potentially it would work as you know
wiping out Islam as a religion and
replacing it with Chinese culture but
the problem is it's too tied to the
culture I don't know how exportable that
is I mean Greta there are countries that
will embrace it me it could have
Singapore embrace it for instance you
know extension kind of kind of culture
as a service stability or coherence as a
service will take care of your you know
their ray occation camps as a service
like I will take care of your your
recalcitrant minorities and realign them
and then will provide a system for
connecting up your citizens but see the
thing is I think it's too tied to the
the Confucian system you get it and the
Chinese culture in in general yeah I
agree with you that's why I'm less
concerned about it perhaps than sums up
the Chinese want to build their country
that way let them have at it right right
it does not seem likely to be the kind
of thing that would spread though as you
do so as you point out
the technology the underlying technology
is likely to spread you know every semi
dictator want to be dictator is going to
want to have get their hands on some of
that technology the you know the facial
recognition scanning systems the social
credit systems perhaps so that may not
work in many cultures I don't think that
would work in the United States at least
not currently it may work and it
certainly wouldn't work in a place like
India where there's you know such a vast
amount of incoherence but some of those
technologies reeducation camps might be
one that's exportable it's the
technologies that are likely to be
exportable rather than the the system
itself yeah point technologies it's it's
gonna be tougher maybe they won't be
able to you know create in a box
solution for this it's just not kind of
not going to be possible you know and
and it also that the fact that they're
so n-word looking is and all the data
they're gathering is you know from a
single region is that the all the
products are growing up going to produce
for global audiences everything that's
going to be infused with a is built on
data that's been captured will both seem
kind of clunky you know it's built and
optimized for a Chinese audience say I
mean highly optimized if you're
gathering data from all over the world
like Facebook is right now and they know
two and a half billion people any
product that's developed out of that is
likely going to be superior in meeting
the needs of those those constituent
populations remember they're
contributing little bits of data that
the that's being incorporated into
development of that system little
nuances little things that make it
better make it more effective China is
not getting that China doesn't have it I
think you're right I'm and so I think
probably both of us are less concerned
about China maybe then some people are
you know China may do its thing and it
may be weird and we may not like it but
as long as it's not spreading around the
world why should we care yeah correct I
mean they are spreading to a certain
extent they're exerting influence you
saw that you know the South Park thing
and you saw they the NBA folding like
you know a deck of cards it's like yeah
just that kind of influence spread is is
not something we we should put up with
ya that's an economic and that's again
where our goddamn corporations worship
the almighty dollar over any higher
values right well they're forcing them
into alignment is the fastest model so
you know we need we need a you know the
resistance Network if it was able to
actually set the value system for those
corporations they would be potentially
resistant to that and the companies
would say mtech Ike exactly that's the
alternative and we do have examples give
them credit both Google and Facebook
have not been willing to play the game
with the Chinese at least so far clearly
Google would kind of like to figure out
how to do it but they haven't you know
the real offender to my mind you know is
Cisco people don't realize this but
Cisco is the ones that help the Chinese
design their Great Firewall they they
have essentially were the enabling
catalyst for all China has done in terms
of managing their information flows and
so they've been a very bad citizen and I
would like to see something like the
resistance put a thumb on corporations
and say you know you really shouldn't be
empowering totalitarian dictators yep
and the others NBA examples a fine
example unfortunately hyper capitalism
you know you know the NBA sees their
next big market and so they don't give
two shits about Chinese culture or
coherence but they just see the
possibility of losing out to you know a
large dollar denominated market so you
know our weakness hyper capitalism gets
exploited by the more coherent system
over in China if we had a more coherent
system our companies would be less
manipulatable correct then they would be
more downsides to actually folding like
that exactly and so you would actually
lose more by trying to you know focus on
the on the come of a new market that may
may or may not pan out all right got a
couple little small things here before
we sign off you've written recently
about how our very much bulked up
counterterrorism efforts are now being
turned on domestic right-wing groups
what's happening what are the
implications well there's been a kind of
a drumbeat in the background you know
whenever there's a been a you know an
attack by a white nationalist to start
to turn and create the legal structures
necessary to have counterterrorism
focus inward and my background is
counterterrorism I did five years in a
Tier one spec ops unit you know one of
the few people were in those units back
then and you know it's it's a pretty
terrifying instrument it's you know we
put incredible amounts of money into it
so far it's been focused almost
exclusively externally you know the
stuff that we do domestically is you
know a little bit you know hyped up law
enforcement the stuff we do externally
is aggressive as all get-out and the the
idea that there's a a white nationalist
threat internally that requires you know
turning a the counter-terrorist system
on domestic targets with its powers of
mass surveillance and you know enemies
lists and stripping national you know
national identity and extradition and
all sorts of stuff along that line is is
pretty scary and I don't want to say it
it's the kind of thing that would run
out of control so if you know if you
first have it focused on these guys who
aren't really affiliated with any
specific group they're you know is
self-activating and it would you know
expect bleed into you know going after
they Anna Phi going after
environmentalists there's an unlimited
number of targets it can start to focus
on very aggressively I mean on a level
of aggression that we haven't seen here
in the States
there's always been a low level of that
with respect to the radical
environmentalists there's always been a
working group in the FBI working on on
elf and some of the other radical
environmentalist groups but again it's
been on the small I think what you're
I'm hearing you say is if you were to
bring any any measurable fraction of the
eighty billion dollars a year we spend
on counterterrorism internationally
it could be extraordinarily ugly in the
United States and the people in the
tactics and and they and the the legal
structures that it would allow them to
operate at the level that they're in
operating internationally yeah I mean if
you know you know about the way they
surveil outside the US versus inside
they mean there's lots and lots of
restrictions
of so many restrictions on what they can
do inside but if those like I say
anti-trump wave comes through and
there's a couple of attacks and and
there's a consensus in the in the US
government to pass this legislation to
kind of route it out you could see
things that we do internationally with
as a matter of course being done
internally
you know use of drones use of use of
renditions use of excessive force and
excessive monitoring you know if you say
okay estimates are that ten percent of
the US population has you know some
level of tacit support for white
nationalism through their actions or
through their words and through their
deeds and trackable online should you
monitor them all like you would a
fundamentalist faction insider and it's
a sighted target country should you
watch all their communications and tag
them and anything suspicious you you
swoop them up you just do the same with
the NFI and you can do the same with
environmentalist it depends on who's in
power name and that's the thing would
say yeah I'm sorry go ahead
say yeah this is thing that both sides
always fucking forget they invent these
new hardball techniques and they forget
that they're not going to be in power
all the time right exactly
there's will always be you know eight
years or 12 years or four years the
other side's going to then now have all
these nice tools for repression that
you've left knowing that whether they
convince themselves that the their
access is on their side are not really
excesses that they're they're fine
they're acceptable and that you know
there's no way the opposition will ever
emerge again if we're tough enough on
them but would give enough powers to a
you know a leader our leader in order to
eradicate them but it never works out
and at least a democracy tide shifts
opposition is in power and and you're
under the gun yep I hope I hope our
country isn't stupid enough to make that
mistake of going down that road and I
read that paper years ago Jesus Christ
let's hope we're smart enough not to do
least do that I
I hope so I'm good you do good work
trying to bring these ideas out last
item before we go is on one of your
websites
you said you'd not sure when the timing
on this was you'd spent the last year
working for the Joint Chiefs or the US
Joint chairman of the US Joint Chiefs of
Staff on his vision for how AGI and
robotics would transform how the joint
force fights in 2035 what did you learn
from that exercise that you can talk to
us about well I mean it was kind of
strange for for the chairman of Joint
Chiefs as they do something called
concepts usually they're on pretty much
mundane topics for how the joint force
would fight today if called upon to do
so this was unusual and that they were
looking 20 years out on autonomous
robotics how that would transform the
joint force you know for the chairman to
kind of push this forward and they
didn't have you know Stephan hand that
was really good at this kind of advanced
autonomous weapon future of warfare kind
of thinking out of the box kind of stuff
so I got brought in on that and you know
there's it's a it's a funny process
going through the process of creating
kind of these concept and creating you
know new ideas and they in the
government it's just you know most of
the most the ideas I have to go through
so many hands and somebody sign off said
everything gets watered down but some
cool stuff came out of at least a you
know in terms of where it has to go in
order to be effective you know things
like you know moving from if you have an
autonomous weapon how do you verify that
is effective really you know autonomous
weapon typically in the past we look at
the you know the error rates generated
by the component parts and the system as
a whole and you can measure that and
determine whether or not it would work
with an autonomous weapon system the the
range of behaviors is is much greater
and it's a black box if it incorporates
like deep learning and you really don't
know you can't do the reverse
engineering you can't do that kind of
pure into the system digitorum and
whether or not it's it's making
decisions in the way that you would deem
effective or not or safe or not while
all you can do is to move towards a
certification process like you would
with a human being
whereas if you have a human being and
you train up
do a certain task the only way you can
actually determine whether or not
they're effective at that task is to put
them into that task in and judge to
behave or certify their behavior and do
it again and again and again and again
until you're satisfied that they'll do
it effectively and there's always a
chance that they'll do it wrong but you
know you have to go with that
certification and the same thing is true
with a with an autonomous system you can
run through simulations and scale that
up substantially but you can also you
know do that in the real world and and
that's how you determine whether or not
it works so little things like that
structure the potential here also is and
this is kind of interesting is that if
you learn something new new tactic new
capability new procedure new maneuver
that you can then capture that in its
totality with nuances now think of it in
terms of like teaching a deep learning
robot how to slice a flying apple with a
samurai sword right you know you saw
that online and saw that you know the
sum our instructor changing the angle of
the blade and getting it perfect so
every time they toss the Apple forward
that the blade cut it perfectly well
think of that
in the context of autonomous weapons and
you come up with this one new technique
and then you could take that technique
and then share it throughout the joint
force and how would the process for that
work is that you would take it test it
run it through thousands of simulations
of millions of simulations billions of
simulations and kind of a simulations
you know command that would then verify
it and certify it and then roll it out
as a capability that can be employed in
all these different systems that are
compatible that has it potentially
completely change everything
yeah the rate of change would go so fast
you know today it seems like military
doctrines operated like a generational
time frame or half oh yeah half a
generation at best ten years as you
point out the beauty of AI is is once
one of them knows it they can all know
it in five minutes right yep and that
you know the the whole weapon system
approach where you you focus on the
hardware and proven it takes 20-30 years
to roll out a new weapon system becomes
less important than the
intelligence of that system and that
intelligence of that system can improve
very quickly over time you know why
you're using it and that changes though
you know kind of perspective on this if
the system's dumb and it can't get
better through experience then you know
it's just a hunk of metal that takes too
long to change systems that learn and
get better from that interaction but
that's that's the system kind of a
system you're shooting for and then the
difference in tactics and strategies you
know an autonomous weapon
you know opens up or truly autonomous
weapon is is like right now we can fire
a weapon and you know like a cruise
missile and you know six hours later it
ends up on target or drone you know it's
it navigates the target he may be make
some Corrections based on the opposition
if it interacts with but it hits a
target and we're pretty comfortable with
that they're pretty de stabilising
granted but they're we're comfortable
with how that works well what about a
system autonomous system that you let go
and two years later it launches it
attack like it's something that actually
drifts very slowly across the Pacific
finds that Chinese Harbor digs itself
into the muck of the Chinese Harbor and
just waits until and gathers information
passively figures out the best targets
to hit at any given moment and then
looks for just a signal that either
should attack or the conditions change
such that it it's ready to attack and
then you you could start to pre position
these things and then you could like
talk about truly to stabilizing
something that can really really change
the the way work war works is that is
that you can roll these things out and
they can slowly you know pre position in
a myriad of locations or you know around
an a potential future enemy like dig
themselves in to landscape and just wait
and then when they conflict hits that's
a true zero day right zero day conflict
it just they pop up wars over they break
all the networks they destroy all the
enemy capabilities they take it out keep
it down you just walk in and also think
of a ramp-up possibility you know with
humans I don't know what it costs the
army to train up a soldier these days
but certainly in the hundreds of
thousands of dollars I would imagine and
it we know it takes a year or two before
a soldier is very effective
right you know a robotic soldier you
know might get the price down at ten
thousand or twenty five thousand dollars
and could build them as fast as you
could build factories so the thing could
you know we could go be back to the ear
of World War two mass warfare with very
few humans involved but you know
literally millions of robots fighting
each other
oh yeah the it also makes possible you
know war between nuclear powers where it
wasn't possible before so like for
instance say we have a conflict with
China over the Spratly Islands so
instead of sending in troops that or
sending in you know aircraft carriers so
they'll become big fat targets that if
they do get destroyed you know five
thousand people die or ten thousand
people die which then is a pretext for
nuclear war I'm too destabilizing too
too dangerous is that we stumble into a
pattern where we demarcate an area like
a hundred miles around the Spratlys and
all those coral reefs and everything
else and it becomes a war between
robotic systems or no human life is lost
but it's really kind of a plant the flag
thing you know this is a cylinder around
that area and that all of the
capabilities that you could throw into
that space determine the victor
determine the one that can actually it
is is superpower conflict but it cannot
strained yes anything that's like World
War two which eventually became
industrial outcome yeah let's say that's
interesting I still think about this is
a game right you define this 100 mile
diameter cylinder maybe a bigger net and
the both sides agree quote-unquote that
we can have at it with non weapons of
mass destruction robots only let's see
who wins right that could go on for a
long time right both sides cranking up
more and more and more and more robots
and drones and bottom crawling ocean
vehicles it will pop up on unexpectedly
at various places it'd be pretty nuts I
would waste a huge amount of resources
of humanity right and then of course the
question is can does it really D not
escalate
you know if the Chinese find themselves
losing are they tempted to escalate to
nuclear weapons say to use EMP forces
just to wipe out all the robots don't
know then you have EMP resistant it's
cool
and it's a good club whose area was
there a published report that people
could get their hands on no there was
not I don't think so there's all just
two most of the stuff Moses stuff ended
up just being you know cotton drafts it
never saw the light of day other than
the senior management that ran through
it you know this stuff will resurface I
mean the good ideas like this never
really die they just kind of good kind
of get shuttled around and there's
champions that kind of stumble into it
if you really have a good idea about
warfare or anything actually it you know
I mean I wrote my first when I was a
forester I wrote my first social
networking report so I called it
personal broadcast networks and it was
popular but people go how do you build
this thing you know we can use a little
bit of this and from the netscape
browser and stuff like that but you know
people kept on working on the idea and
it took me to 2001 to find a company
actually realizing it with the you know
the network approach of usual ads a RSS
blogging system so you know ideas can
tend to come up you know tend to surface
if they're in the right they if they
have the kind of right system that makes
pushing them forward indeed well John
this has been absolutely fascinating
we've covered a tremendous amount of
ground as I expected we would I think
our listeners here will have learned a
whole lot so I want to thank you for
coming on ah my pleasure thanks Jim
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com